<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.6.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/vb_blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/vb_blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2018-01-21T23:09:47+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/vb_blog/</id><title type="html">VB SuryaTeja</title><subtitle>Write an awesome description for your new site here. You can edit this line in _config.yml. It will appear in your document head meta (for Google search results) and in your feed.xml site description.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Welcome to Jekyll!</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/vb_blog/jekyll/update/2017/12/11/welcome-to-jekyll.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Welcome to Jekyll!" /><published>2017-12-11T22:53:14+05:30</published><updated>2017-12-11T22:53:14+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/vb_blog/jekyll/update/2017/12/11/welcome-to-jekyll</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/vb_blog/jekyll/update/2017/12/11/welcome-to-jekyll.html">&lt;p&gt;You’ll find this post in your &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;_posts&lt;/code&gt; directory. Go ahead and edit it and re-build the site to see your changes. You can rebuild the site in many different ways, but the most common way is to run &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;jekyll serve&lt;/code&gt;, which launches a web server and auto-regenerates your site when a file is updated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To add new posts, simply add a file in the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;_posts&lt;/code&gt; directory that follows the convention &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;YYYY-MM-DD-name-of-post.ext&lt;/code&gt; and includes the necessary front matter. Take a look at the source for this post to get an idea about how it works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jekyll also offers powerful support for code snippets:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-ruby&quot; data-lang=&quot;ruby&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;print_hi&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;puts&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;Hi, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;si&quot;&gt;#{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;si&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;print_hi&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;'Tom'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;#=&amp;gt; prints 'Hi, Tom' to STDOUT.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check out the &lt;a href=&quot;https://jekyllrb.com/docs/home&quot;&gt;Jekyll docs&lt;/a&gt; for more info on how to get the most out of Jekyll. File all bugs/feature requests at &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jekyll/jekyll&quot;&gt;Jekyll’s GitHub repo&lt;/a&gt;. If you have questions, you can ask them on &lt;a href=&quot;https://talk.jekyllrb.com/&quot;&gt;Jekyll Talk&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">You’ll find this post in your _posts directory. Go ahead and edit it and re-build the site to see your changes. You can rebuild the site in many different ways, but the most common way is to run jekyll serve, which launches a web server and auto-regenerates your site when a file is updated.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What is Machine Learning!</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/vb_blog/machine/learning/2017/10/14/NLP-Notes.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What is Machine Learning!" /><published>2017-10-14T17:10:21+05:30</published><updated>2017-10-14T17:10:21+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/vb_blog/machine/learning/2017/10/14/NLP-Notes</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/vb_blog/machine/learning/2017/10/14/NLP-Notes.html">&lt;h3 id=&quot;natural-language-processing&quot;&gt;Natural Language Processing:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Natural language processing (NLP) is a field of computer science, artificial intelligence and computational linguistics concerned with the interactions between computers and human (natural) languages, and, in particular, concerned with programming computers to fruitfully process large natural language corpora. Challenges in natural language processing frequently involve speech recognition, natural language understanding, natural language generation (frequently from formal, machine-readable logical forms), connecting language and machine perception, dialog systems, or some combination thereof.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Important Terms in NLP:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Language Model&lt;/strong&gt; : A language model is a function, or an algorithm for learning such a function, that captures the salient statistical characteristics of the distribution of sequences of words in a natural language, typically allowing one to make probabilistic predictions of the next word given preceding ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Neural Language Models&lt;/strong&gt; : A neural network language model is a language model based on Neural Networks , exploiting their ability to learn distributed representations to reduce the impact of the curse of dimensionality. In the context of learning algorithms, the curse of dimensionality refers to the need for huge numbers of training examples when learning highly complex functions. When the number of input variables increases, the number of required examples can grow exponentially. The curse of dimensionality arises when a huge number of different combinations of values of the input variables must be discriminated from each other, and the learning algorithm needs at least one example per relevant combination of values. In the context of language models, the problem comes from the huge number of possible sequences of words, e.g., with a sequence of 10 words taken from a vocabulary of 100,000 there are 1050 possible sequences…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Morphology&lt;/strong&gt; : In linguistics, morphology is the study of words, how they are formed, and their relationship to other words in the same language.It analyzes the structure of words and parts of words, such as stems, root words, prefixes, and suffixes. Morphology also looks at parts of speech, intonation and stress, and the ways context can change a word’s pronunciation and meaning. Morphology differs from morphological typology, which is the classification of languages based on their use of words and lexicology, which is the study of words and how they make up a language’s vocabulary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lemmatisation&lt;/strong&gt; : Lemmatisation (or lemmatization) in linguistics is the process of grouping together the inflected forms of a word so they can be analysed as a single item, identified by the word’s lemma, or dictionary form.
In computational linguistics, lemmatisation is the algorithmic process of determining the lemma of a word based on its intended meaning. Unlike stemming, lemmatisation depends on correctly identifying the intended part of speech and meaning of a word in a sentence, as well as within the larger context surrounding that sentence, such as neighboring sentences or even an entire document. As a result, developing efficient lemmatisation algorithms is an open area of research&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Natural Language Processing:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What is Machine Learning - 3!</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/vb_blog/machine/learning/2017/10/14/What-is-Machine-Learning-part-3.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What is Machine Learning - 3!" /><published>2017-10-14T17:10:21+05:30</published><updated>2017-10-14T17:10:21+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/vb_blog/machine/learning/2017/10/14/What-is-Machine-Learning-part-3</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/vb_blog/machine/learning/2017/10/14/What-is-Machine-Learning-part-3.html">&lt;h3 id=&quot;regression&quot;&gt;Regression.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;linear-regression&quot;&gt;Linear Regression&lt;/h4&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Regression.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What is Machine Learning - 2!</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/vb_blog/machine/learning/2017/10/14/What-is-Machine-Learning-part-2.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What is Machine Learning - 2!" /><published>2017-10-14T17:10:21+05:30</published><updated>2017-10-14T17:10:21+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/vb_blog/machine/learning/2017/10/14/What-is-Machine-Learning-part-2</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/vb_blog/machine/learning/2017/10/14/What-is-Machine-Learning-part-2.html">&lt;h3 id=&quot;classification&quot;&gt;Classification.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;in this post we will explore about supervised learning,which is one of the categories in ML. Two generic problems in Supervised Learning are Classification and Regression. we are going to use python language which is a very popular among ML community. scikit-learn is a popular ML library in python, which use compiled scientific python libraries under the hood to make the computations smooth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;a-simple-classification-problem&quot;&gt;A Simple classification problem:&lt;/h4&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Classification.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What is Machine Learning - 1!</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/vb_blog/machine/learning/2017/10/14/What-is-Machine-Learning-part-1.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What is Machine Learning - 1!" /><published>2017-10-14T17:10:21+05:30</published><updated>2017-10-14T17:10:21+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/vb_blog/machine/learning/2017/10/14/What-is-Machine-Learning-part-1</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/vb_blog/machine/learning/2017/10/14/What-is-Machine-Learning-part-1.html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;introduction-to-machine-learning&quot;&gt;Introduction to Machine Learning.&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;in this post i will help you and myself better understanding about what is it all  about &lt;strong&gt;Machine Learning&lt;/strong&gt;.why every one is so talking as if it is the new Electricity, and why is it so important?.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Machine Learning is a subset of &lt;strong&gt;Artificial Intelligence&lt;/strong&gt;. In general what is meant by AI(Artificial Intelligence, will use this a lot), the ability to replicate an intelligent behavior which we humans only can boast of on the planet earth, other than a lot of Animals,Birds who can posses a limited intelligent behavior. but the real question is can the machines be really smart as humans? we have to wait and see for that.there are evidence that a machine can match the human if not better in certain tasks, be it playing chess,go or recognizing the pictures of animals, writing &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ibm.com/blogs/research/2017/03/road-not-taken-computer-generated-poetry/&quot;&gt;poetry&lt;/a&gt;(IBM Watson has done that).they are learning, eventually with the recent advancements in the Quantum Computing they may reach a point where they could replicate the intelligent behavior.though AI has its flaws , a lot of people  most notably Tesla’s CEO has claimed the Raise of AI could lead to an Apocalypse. there are recent incidents like the one in Facebook labs , the AI bots started creating their own language and started communicating.there is a lot to hope amid all these things, AI can lead to a better life of Human Beings, or it can end it for once and all.we can only wait and watch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Okay, now back to our original goal of this post describing what is Machine Learning. Machine learning is an application of artificial intelligence (AI) that provides systems the ability to automatically learn and improve from experience without being explicitly programmed. Machine learning focuses on the development of computer programs that can access data and use it learn for themselves. how exactly machines are going to be learning from experience with out explicit programming, so you may wonder we may need not to program machines for this process, no! wait there, in computer terms we have to program the Machine to do the learning from experience.there is a technical gap between what people usually thought about what is ML and what it actually is. there is some math going under the hoods, of course we have a lot of ML libraries to wrap the math for us and provided the higher level API just even a new guy to programming can use if he/she has the complete understanding of the ML problem they are solving.so what kind of problems ML could solve?. you can solve various problems include classification, regression, clustering problems. going forward we will learn about each of the problem kind which ML can solve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Machine Learning Types&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Machine Learning can be divided into the following categories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;supervised learning.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;unsupervised learning.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;semi supervised learning.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;reinforcement learning.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Machine learning can solve problems of various types from fraud detection in credit cards to predicting election polls, from image processing to natural language processing, from speech recognition to text generation. Machine Learning can boost the Data Science field by getting better insights from the data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Software to do Machine Learning&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The popular programming languages for machine learning are Python, R, Scala(Spark). My preferred language to do machine learning is Python since it is opensource and easier to program ML concepts in Python and a ton’s of open source libraries available to do pretty much anything in python. Following are some best curated list of libraries available for machine learning in python.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;scientific python Libraries:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Numpy&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pandas&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Scipy&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Matplotlib(for plotting)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;scientific Python Libraries are very useful to preprocess the data and prepare datast for ML models. ideally you would want to represent the data in numpy arrays as they are very fast and memory efficient. The popular ML libraries like Tensorflow and scikit learn operates on top of numpy arrays. pandas is a data analysis toolkit, which again operates on top of numpy arrays for heavy numerical lifting to perform the analysis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ML Libraries:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Tensorflow&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Scikit-learn&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tensorflow is probably the most used ML library by academics, researchers and in production by big guns in the corporate world in the last couple of years. scikit learn is the most popular another ML library which is around for a long time, and is the number one ML library in Python being used before tensorflow arrival.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;in the following series of posts we will mostly discuss about the first 3 types of ML categories, becuase Reinforcement is an altogether big and much evolving field , we will talk about it in a separate series of posts.
in the next post i will show you different types of problems in the categories mentioned above and how to solve them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Continue part 2&lt;/a&gt;….!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Introduction to Machine Learning.</summary></entry></feed>